<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">
  <title>The Power of Evolution</title>
  <para>
    Software is normally developed in a very precise, deterministic way.  The behaviour of a
    computer is governed by strict logical rules.  A computer invariably does exactly what
    it is told to do.
  </para>
  <para>
    When writing a program to solve a particular problem, software developers will identify
    the necessary sub-tasks that the program must perform.  Algorithms are chosen and
    implemented for each task.  The completed program becomes a detailed specification of
    exactly how to get from A to B.  Every aspect is carefully designed by its developers
    who must understand how the various components interact to deliver the program's
    functionality.
  </para>
  <para>
    This prescriptive approach to solving problems with computers has served us well and is
    responsible for most of the software applications that we use today.  However, it is not
    without limitations.
    Solutions to problems are constrained by the intuition, knowledge and prejudices
    of those who develop the software.
    <emphasis>The programmers have to know exactly how to solve the problem.</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
    Another characteristic of the prescriptive approach that is sometimes problematic is
    that it is best suited to finding exact answers.  Not all problems have exact solutions,
    and some that do may be too computationally expensive to solve.  Sometimes it is
    more useful to be able to find an approximate answer quickly than to waste time searching
    for a better solution.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>What are Evolutionary Algorithms?</title>
    <indexterm><primary>evolutionary algorithm</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Darwin, Charles</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Evolutionary algorithms (EAs) are inspired by the biological model of evolution and
      natural selection first proposed by Charles Darwin in 1859.
      In the natural world, evolution helps species adapt to their environments.
      Environmental factors that influence the survival prospects of an organism
      include climate, availability of food and the dangers of predators.
    </para>
    <indexterm><primary>natural selection</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Species change over the course of many generations.
      Mutations occur randomly.  Some mutations will be advantageous, but many will be
      useless or detrimental.  Progress comes from the feedback provided by non-random
      natural selection.
      For example, organisms that can survive for long periods without water will be
      more likely to thrive in dry conditions than those that can't.
      Likewise, animals that can run fast will be more successful at evading predators
      than their slower rivals.
      If a random genetic modification helps an organism to survive and to reproduce,
      that modification will itself survive and spread throughout the population, via
      the organism's offspring.
    </para>
    <para>
      Evolutionary algorithms are based on a simplified model of this biological evolution.
      To solve a particular problem we create an environment in which potential
      solutions can evolve.  The environment is shaped by the parameters of the problem
      and encourages the evolution of good solutions.
    </para>
    <indexterm><primary>evolutionary computation</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      The field of Evolutionary Computation encompasses several types of evolutionary
      algorithm.  These include <emphasis>Genetic Algorithms</emphasis> (GAs),
      <emphasis>Evolution Strategies</emphasis>, <emphasis>Genetic Programming</emphasis>
      (GP), <emphasis>Evolutionary Programming</emphasis> and <emphasis>Learning
      Classifier Systems</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <indexterm><primary>genetic algorithms</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      The most common type of evolutionary algorithm is the generational genetic
      algorithm.  We'll cover other EA variants in later chapters but, for now,
      all of the evolutionary algorithms that we meet will be some kind of generational
      GA.
    </para>
    <indexterm><primary>fitness function</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>population</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      The basic outline of a generational GA is as follows (most other EA variants are
      broadly similar).
      A <emphasis>population</emphasis> of candidate solutions is iteratively evolved
      over many <emphasis>generations</emphasis>.  Mimicking the concept of
      natural selection in biology, the survival of candidates (or their offspring)
      from generation to generation in an EA is governed by a <emphasis>fitness
      function</emphasis> that evaluates each candidate according to how close it is to
      the desired outcome, and a <emphasis>selection strategy</emphasis> that favours
      the better solutions.
      Over time, the quality of the solutions in the population should improve.
      If the program is successful, we can terminate the evolution once it has found
      a solution that is good enough.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>An Example</title>
      <para>
        Now that we have introduced the basic concepts and terminology, I will attempt
        to illustrate by way of an example. Suppose that we want to use evolution to generate
        a particular character string, for example "HELLO WORLD".  This is a contrived example
        in as much as it assumes that we don't know how to create such a string and that
        evolution is the best approach available to us.  However, bear with me as this simple
        example is useful for demonstrating exactly how the evolutionary approach works.
      </para>
      <para>
        Each candidate solution in our population will be a string.  We'll use a fixed-length
        representation so that each string is 11 characters long.  Each character in a string
        will be one of the 27 valid characters (the upper case letters 'A' to 'Z' plus the space
        character).
      </para>
      <para>
        For the fitness function we'll use the simple approach of assigning a candidate
        solution one point for each position in the string that has the correct character.
        For the string "HELLO WORLD" this gives a maximum possible fitness score of 11 (the
        length of the string).
      </para>
      <para>
        The first task for the evolutionary algorithm is to randomly generate the initial
        population. We can use any size population that we choose.
        Typical EA population sizes can vary from tens to thousands of individuals.
        For this example we will use a population size of 10.
        After the initialisation of the population we might have the following candidates
        (fitness scores in brackets):
        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>
  1.  GERZUNFXCEN  (1)
  2.  HSFDAHDMUYZ  (1)
  3.  UQ IGARHGJN  (0)
  4.  ZASIB WSUVP  (2)
  5.  XIXROIUAZBH  (1)
  6.  VDLGCWMBFYA  (1)
  7.  SY YUHYRSEE  (0)
  8.  EUSVBIVFHFK  (0)
  9.  HHENRFZAMZH  (1)
  10. UJBBDFZPLCN  (0)
          </programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </para>
      <para>
        None of these candidate solutions is particularly good. The best (number 4) has just two
        characters out of eleven that match the target string (the space character and the 'W').
      </para>
      <para>
        The next step is to select candidates based on their fitness and use them to create
        a new generation.  One technique for favouring the selection of fitter candidates over
        weaker candidates is to assign each candidate a selection probability proportionate to
        its fitness.
      </para>
      <indexterm><primary>fitness-proportionate selection</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>selection</primary><secondary>fitness-proportionate</secondary></indexterm>
      <para>
        If we use <emphasis>fitness-proportionate selection</emphasis>, none of the candidates
        with zero fitness will be selected and the candidate with a fitness of 2 is twice as likely
        to be selected as any of the candidates with a fitness of 1. For the next step we need to
        select 10 parents, so it is obvious that some of the fit candidates are going to be selected
        multiple times.
      </para>
      <indexterm><primary>cross-over</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        Now that we have some parents, we can breed the next generation.  We do this via a process
        called <emphasis>cross-over</emphasis>, which is analogous to sexual reproduction in biology.
        For each pair of parents, a cross-over point is selected randomly.  Assuming that the first
        two randomly selected parents are numbers 2 and 4, if the cross-over occurs after the
        first four characters, we will get the following offspring:
        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>
  Parent 1:     <emphasis role="bold">HSFDAHDMUYZ</emphasis>
  Parent 2:     ZASIB WSUVP

  Offspring 1:  <emphasis role="bold">HSFD</emphasis>B WSUVP
  Offspring 2:  ZASI<emphasis role="bold">AHDMUYZ</emphasis>
          </programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </para>
      <indexterm><primary>mutation</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        This recombination has given us two new candidates for the next generation, one of which is
        better than either of the parents (offspring 1 has a fitness score of 3).  This shows how
        cross-over can lead towards better solutions.  However, looking at the initial population as
        a whole, we can see that no combination of cross-overs will ever result in a candidate with
        a fitness higher than 6.  This is because, among all 10 original candidates, there are only 6
        positions in which we have the correct character.  This can be mitigated to some extent by
        increasing the size of the population.  With 100 individuals in the initial population we
        would be much more likely to have the necessary building blocks for a perfect solution, but
        there is no guarantee.  This is where <emphasis>mutation</emphasis> comes in.
      </para>
      <para>
        Mutation is implemented by modifying each character in a string according to some small
        probability, say 0.02 or 0.05.  This means that any single individual will be changed only
        slightly by mutation, or perhaps not at all.
      </para>
      <para>
        By applying mutation to each of the offspring produced by cross-over we will occasionally
        introduce correct characters in new positions.  We will also occasionally remove correct
        characters but these bad mutations are unlikely to survive selection in the next generation,
        so this is not a big problem.  Advantageous mutations will be propagated by cross-over and
        selection and will quickly spread throughout the population.
      </para>
      <para>
        After repeating this process for dozens or perhaps even hundreds of generations we will
        eventually converge on our desired solution.
      </para>
      <para>
        This is a convoluted process for finding a string that we already knew to start with.
        However, as we shall see in the remainder of this book, the evolutionary approach
        generalises to deal with problems where we don't know what the best solution is and
        therefore can't encode that knowledge in our fitness function.
      </para>        
      <para>
        The important point demonstrated by this example is that we can arrive at a satisfactory
        solution without having to enumerate every possible candidate in the search space.
        Even for this trivial example, a brute force search would involve generating and
        checking approximately 5.6 quadrillion strings.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>The Outline of an Evolutionary Algorithm</title>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <title>Genesis</title>
          <para>
            Create an initial set (population) of <literal>n</literal> candidate solutions.
            This may be done entirely randomly or the population may be seeded with some
            hand-picked candidates.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <title>Evaluation</title>
          <para>
            Evaluate each member of the population using some fitness function.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <title>Survival of the Fittest</title>
          <indexterm><primary>selection</primary></indexterm>
          <para>
            Select a number of members of the evaluated population, favouring those
            with higher fitness scores.  These will be the parents of the next generation.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <title>Evolution</title>
          <indexterm><primary>cross-over</primary></indexterm>
          <indexterm><primary>mutation</primary></indexterm>
          <para>
            Generate a new population of offspring by randomly altering and/or combining
            elements of the parent candidates.  The evolution is performed by one or more
            <emphasis>evolutionary operators</emphasis>.  The most common operators are
            cross-over and mutation.
            Cross-over takes two parents, cuts them each into two or more pieces and recombines
            the pieces to create two new offspring.  Mutation copies an individual but with
            small, random modifications (such as flipping a bit from zero to one).
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <title>Iteration</title>
          <para>
            Repeat steps 2-4 until a satisfactory solution is found or some other termination
            condition is met (such as the number of generations or elapsed time).
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>When are Evolutionary Algorithms Useful?</title>
    <para>
      Evolutionary algorithms are typically used to provide good approximate
      solutions to problems that cannot be solved easily using other techniques.
      Many optimisation problems fall into this category.  It may be too
      computationally-intensive to find an exact solution but sometimes a near-optimal
      solution is sufficient.  In these situations evolutionary techniques can be
      effective.  Due to their random nature, evolutionary algorithms are never guaranteed
      to find an optimal solution for any problem, but they will often find a good solution
      if one exists.
    </para>
    <para>
      One example of this kind of optimisation problem is the challenge of timetabling.
      Schools and universities must arrange room and staff allocations to suit the needs
      of their curriculum.  There are several constraints that must be satisfied.
      A member of staff can only be in one place at a time, they can only teach classes
      that are in their area of expertise, rooms cannot host lessons if they are already
      occupied, and classes must not clash with other classes taken by the same students.
      This is a combinatorial problem and known to be NP-Hard.
      It is not feasible to exhaustively search for the optimal timetable due to the huge
      amount of computation involved.  Instead, heuristics must be used.
      Genetic algorithms have proven to be a successful way of generating satisfactory
      solutions to many scheduling problems.
    </para>
    <para>
      Evolutionary algorithms can also be used to tackle problems that humans don't really
      know how to solve.
      An EA, free of any human preconceptions or biases, can generate surprising solutions
      that are comparable to, or better than, the best human-generated efforts.
      It is merely necessary that we can recognise a good solution if
      it were presented to us, even if we don't know <emphasis>how</emphasis> to create a
      good solution.
      In other words, we need to be able to formulate an effective fitness function.
    </para>
    <para>
      Engineers working for NASA know a lot about physics.  They know exactly which
      characteristics make for a good communications antenna.  But the process
      of designing an antenna so that it has the necessary properties is hard.  Even
      though the engineers know what is required from the final antenna, they may not know
      how to design the antenna so that it satisfies those requirements.
    </para>
    <para>
      NASA's Evolvable Systems Group has used evolutionary algorithms to successfully
      evolve antennas for use on satellites.  These evolved antennas have irregular shapes
      with no obvious symmetry (one of these antennas is pictured below).
      It is unlikely that a human expert would have arrived at such an unconventional design.
      Despite this, when tested these antennas proved to be extremely well adapted to their
      purpose.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="antenna.jpg" format="JPG" width="50%" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://ti.arc.nasa.gov/projects/esg/research/antenna.htm">NASA Evolvable Systems Group</link>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <section>
      <title>Pre-requisites</title>
      <indexterm><primary>encoding</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        There are two requirements that must be met before an evolutionary algorithm can
        be used for a particular problem.
        Firstly, we need a way to encode candidate solutions to the problem.  The simplest
        encoding, and that used by many genetic algorithms, is a bit string.  Each candidate
        is simply a sequence of zeros and ones.
        This encoding makes cross-over and mutation very straightforward, but that does not
        mean that you cannot use more complicated representations.  In fact, we will see
        several instances of more advanced candidate representations in later chapters.
        As long as we can devise a scheme for evolving the candidates, there really is no
        restriction on the types that we can use.
        Genetic programming (GP) is a good example of this.  GP evolves computer programs
        represented as syntax trees.
      </para>
      <indexterm><primary>fitness function</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        The second requirement for applying evolutionary algorithms is that there must be a
        way of evaluating partial solutions to the problem - the fitness function.  It is
        not sufficient to evaluate solutions as right or wrong, the fitness score needs to
        indicate <emphasis>how right</emphasis> or, if your glass is half empty,
        <emphasis>how wrong</emphasis> a candidate solution is.  So a function that returns
        either 0 or 1 is useless.  A function that returns a score on a scale of 1 - 100 is
        better.  We need shades of grey, not just black and white, since this is how the
        algorithm guides the random evolution to find increasingly better solutions.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Implementing Evolutionary Algorithms</title>
    <para>
      If an evolutionary algorithm is a good fit for a particular problem, there are plenty of
      options when it comes to implementing it. 
      You may choose to use a high-level programming language for simplicity, or a low-level
      language for performance.
      You could write all of the code yourself from scratch, or you could reuse pre-written
      components and libraries.
      In this book we will necessarily be using one particular approach, but it is worth noting
      that there are alternatives.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Choice of Programming Language</title>
      <para>
        Evolutionary algorithms can be implemented in any general purpose programming language.
        Most programmers will simply choose the language that they are most comfortable with.
        A quick web search will return examples of evolutionary programs written in C, C++,
        Java, C#, Python, Ruby, Perl, Lisp and several other languages.
      </para>
      <para>
        Performance may be a consideration when choosing a language.
        Almost all evolutionary algorithms are CPU-bound.  For this reason, compiled languages
        typically offer better EA performance than interpreted languages.  For
        short-lived programs the difference is unlikely to be significant, but for
        long-running programs it could be considerable.
      </para>
      <indexterm><primary>Java</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        If you can recall the title of this book it should come as no surprise that we will be
        using Java for all of the example code.  Java offers a good balance of performance,
        ease-of-use and a rich standard library.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Evolution Frameworks</title>
      <indexterm><primary>frameworks</primary></indexterm>
      <para>
        As we saw above, the basic outline of an evolutionary algorithm is fairly
        straightforward.  It consists of a main loop that performs one generation per iteration,
        supplemented by a few functions to perform fitness evaluation, selection and
        mutation/cross-over.  When implementing a simple EA, writing this structural code is
        not particularly onerous.  However, if you write many different evolutionary
        programs, as we will be doing in the remainder of this book, you end up writing code
        that is very similar over and over again.
      </para>
      <para>
        A good programmer will usually want to extract and reuse this common code.
        Once you have done this, you have the basis of an evolutionary computation framework.
        Typically this will consist of an evolution engine that is reusable and that can
        accept different functions to customise fitness evaluation, selection and evolutionary
        operators.
      </para>
      <para>
        An alternative to using a home-grown framework is to choose a ready-made one.  There
        are open source evolutionary computation frameworks available for most programming languages.
        For popular languages, such as C, C++ and Java, there are dozens.
      </para>
      <para>
        The advantage of a
        ready-made framework that is used by many other programmers is that it will have been well
        tested and should be free of significant bugs and performance problems.  It may also provide
        advanced features such as parallel and/or distributed processing.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
