<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">
  <title>The Watchmaker Framework</title>
  <indexterm significance="preferred"><primary>Watchmaker Framework</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    The Watchmaker Framework for Evolutionary Computation is an extensible, high-performance,
    object-oriented framework for implementing platform-independent evolutionary algorithms
    in Java.
    It is freely available under a permissive Open Source licence.  It can be downloaded from
    <link href="https://watchmaker.dev.java.net">https://watchmaker.dev.java.net</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    This chapter introduces the core components of the Watchmaker Framework and shows how
    they can be used to implement simple evolutionary algorithms such as the one outlined
    in the previous chapter.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>The Evolution Engine</title>
    <indexterm><primary>ConcurrentEvolutionEngine</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>EvolutionEngine</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      The central object of an evolutionary program built with the Watchmaker Framework is
      the evolution engine.  An evolution engine is a general-purpose implementation of
      the evolutionary algorithm outline from chapter 1.
    </para>
    <para>
      The framework provides multiple implementations of the
      <classname>EvolutionEngine</classname> interface, but the one that you will
      usually want to use is the <classname>ConcurrentEvolutionEngine</classname>.  As its
      name suggests, it takes advantage of the parallel processing facilities of your
      computer in order to speed-up the evolutionary process.
    </para>
    <para>
      An <classname>EvolutionEngine</classname> has a single generic type parameter
      that indicates the type of object that it can evolve.  Creating an engine that
      can evolve Java <classname>String</classname>s would look something like this:
    </para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[EvolutionEngine<String> engine
    = new ConcurrentEvolutionEngine<String>(candidateFactory,
                                            evolutionaryOperator,
                                            fitnessEvaluator,
                                            selectionStrategy,
                                            rng);]]>
      </programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>
      Once you have created an <classname>EvolutionEngine</classname>, your program is as
      simple as calling the <methodname>evolve</methodname> method with appropriate
      arguments.
      However, as you can see from the code snippet above, there is a little bit of work to
      be done first in order to create an <classname>EvolutionEngine</classname> that is
      configured appropriately for the given problem.
      The constructor of the <classname>ConcurrentEvolutionEngine</classname> class requires
      five objects.  These are:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>A Candidate Factory</listitem>
      <listitem>An Evolutionary Operator</listitem>
      <listitem>A Fitness Evaluator</listitem>
      <listitem>A Selection Strategy</listitem>
      <listitem>A Random Number Generator</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The Candidate Factory</title>
    <indexterm><primary>CandidateFactory</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      The first object that needs to be plugged into the evolution engine is a candidate
      factory.  Every evolutionary simulation must start with an initial population of
      candidate solutions and the factory is the mechanism by which the evolution engine
      creates this population.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Selection Strategy</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Evolutionary Operators</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The Fitness Evaluator</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Random Number Generator</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Putting it all Together</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
    <section>
      <title>Termination Conditions</title>
      <para>TODO</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Evolution Observers</title>
      <para>TODO</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
